<p>All of the platform's spatial data lives in <strong>Amazon S3</strong> as cloud-native files served via byte-range reads. Metadata, policies, and operational state live in <strong>Amazon DynamoDB</strong>. This document specifies the layouts of both.</p>
<h1>S3 layout</h1>
<p>A single S3 bucket holds all spatial data, organised by prefix. A single bucket — rather than one per data class — simplifies IAM (a single bucket ARN), lifecycle management (one S3 Lifecycle policy with per-prefix rules), and administration. S3 has no per-bucket charges, so prefixes are purely organisational.</p>
<ac:structured-macro ac:name="code"><ac:plain-text-body><![CDATA[spatial-data-bucket/
├── cogs/                       Raster sources (COGs, organised by region/dataset/date)
├── elevation/                  DEMs (special-cased COGs)
├── mosaics/                    MosaicJSON descriptors (raster mosaics)
├── pmtiles/                    Live vector tiles (atomic-swap target)
│   └── staging/                Generation output before promotion
├── source/                     Hive-partitioned GeoParquet (authoritative vector data)
│   └── {dataset}/z={z}/x={x}/y={y}/data.parquet
├── drafts/                     Edit session artefacts (delta/diff PMTiles, check results)
│   └── {dataset}/{session}/
├── landing/                    User uploads — triggers the editing pipeline
│   └── {dataset}/{job}/
├── history/                    Per-row history (SCD2)
│   └── {dataset}/
├── metadata/
│   └── dataset_events/         Per-dataset event log (Parquet)
├── viewer/                     Static web map viewer
└── map-client/                 Map client application bundle]]></ac:plain-text-body></ac:structured-macro>
<p>Each prefix has a single purpose and a defined producer/consumer relationship.</p>
<table><tbody><tr><th>Prefix</th><th>Producer</th><th>Consumer</th></tr><tr><td><code>cogs/</code></td><td>External processes (data ingest)</td><td>Raster tile server, coverages API</td></tr><tr><td><code>elevation/</code></td><td>External processes</td><td>Raster tile server</td></tr><tr><td><code>mosaics/</code></td><td>External processes or admin scripts</td><td>Raster tile server, WMTS proxy</td></tr><tr><td><code>pmtiles/</code></td><td>Promotion function (atomic copy from staging)</td><td>Vector tile server</td></tr><tr><td><code>pmtiles/staging/</code></td><td>Generation task</td><td>Promotion function</td></tr><tr><td><code>source/</code></td><td>Validation task</td><td>Query layer, OGC Features API</td></tr><tr><td><code>drafts/</code></td><td>Validation and generation tasks</td><td>Reviewer (via vector tile server), editing API</td></tr><tr><td><code>landing/</code></td><td>Clients (via presigned upload)</td><td>Workflow engine (triggered by storage event)</td></tr><tr><td><code>history/</code></td><td>Promotion function (writes deltas); history vacuum (compacts)</td><td>Query layer (point-in-time queries)</td></tr><tr><td><code>metadata/dataset_events/</code></td><td>Promotion function (writes events); event-log compactor (compacts)</td><td>Admin and operations queries</td></tr></tbody></table>
<p>The same shape, viewed as a flow:</p>
<ac:structured-macro ac:name="mermaid-cloud"><ac:plain-text-body><![CDATA[flowchart LR
    CLIENT[Client / external ingest] -- presigned PUT --> LAND[("landing/<br/>uploads")]
    CLIENT -. external batch .-> COG[("cogs/<br/>raster sources")]
    LAND --> VAL[Validation task]
    VAL --> SRC[("source/<br/>GeoParquet partitions")]
    VAL --> DRAFT[("drafts/<br/>delta + diff PMTiles")]
    SRC --> GEN[Generation task]
    GEN --> STAGE[("pmtiles/staging/")]
    STAGE --> PROMO[Promotion Lambda]
    PROMO --> LIVE[("pmtiles/<br/>live tiles")]
    PROMO --> HIST[("history/<br/>SCD2 deltas")]
    PROMO --> EVT[("metadata/dataset_events/")]
    LIVE --> VTS[Vector tile server]
    SRC --> QL[Query layer / Features API]
    COG --> RTS[Raster tile server]
    COG --> MOS[("mosaics/<br/>MosaicJSON")] --> RTS
    DRAFT --> VTS]]></ac:plain-text-body></ac:structured-macro>
<p>Each prefix is the only thing some component writes to and the only thing some other component reads from. That one-producer-one-consumer property is what keeps lifecycle rules, IAM, and reasoning about staleness manageable.</p>
<h2>Vector data: GeoParquet with Hive-style spatial partitioning</h2>
<p>The authoritative storage for vector features is <strong>GeoParquet</strong> under <code>source/</code>. Files are organised by tile coordinates in a Hive-style directory layout:</p>
<ac:structured-macro ac:name="code"><ac:plain-text-body><![CDATA[source/{dataset_id}/z={z}/x={x}/y={y}/data.parquet]]></ac:plain-text-body></ac:structured-macro>
<p>The tile coordinates correspond to a chosen partition zoom (typically zoom 6). At zoom 6, the world is divided into a grid of 4096 tiles (64×64), giving partitions that are coarse enough to limit object count but fine enough that bbox queries only read a handful of files.</p>
<p><strong>Why this layout:</strong></p>
<ul><li><strong>Predicate pushdown on partition keys.</strong> Analytical engines (DuckDB, BigQuery, Athena, Spark) understand the Hive <code>key=value</code> directory convention natively. A bbox query is translated into a tile-set query and only the matching partitions are read.</li><li><strong>Incremental edits.</strong> When a feature is edited, only the partitions whose tiles intersect the feature's geometry are rewritten. An 800,000-feature dataset can absorb a single-feature edit by rewriting a few small Parquet files.</li><li><strong>Ecosystem compatibility.</strong> GeoParquet is readable by QGIS, GeoPandas, and any modern data tool that supports Parquet plus geometry.</li></ul>
<p><strong>Cross-partition writes.</strong> Features that span multiple tiles are written to every partition they intersect, with their full geometry (not clipped). This:</p>
<ul><li>Avoids the need to reassemble clipped geometries at read time.</li><li>Makes single-partition reads complete (every feature touching the query bbox is present in the partitions read).</li></ul>
<p>The cost is that a single feature may appear multiple times across partitions. This is handled at read time.</p>
<p><strong>Read-time deduplication.</strong> Every query reads with <code>DISTINCT ON (id)</code> semantics (or an equivalent window function for distance-ordered results). The result is one row per feature identifier, regardless of how many partitions held it. Every dataset must declare an <code>id_column</code> in its registry entry; the validation task enforces this on intake.</p>
<ac:structured-macro ac:name="info"><ac:rich-text-body><p><strong>In plain terms.</strong> writes pay the cost of duplicating a straddling feature across the tiles it touches; reads pay the cost of collapsing those duplicates back into one. The alternative — clipping geometries at partition boundaries on write — pushes the cost onto every read instead, where it is harder to do correctly.</p></ac:rich-text-body></ac:structured-macro>
<h2>Vector tiles: PMTiles</h2>
<p>Vector tiles are stored as <strong>PMTiles</strong> archives at <code>pmtiles/{dataset_id}.pmtiles</code>. PMTiles is a single-file format that packs all tiles of a dataset into one archive with an index that supports HTTP byte-range reads. S3's range-read semantics are the substrate that makes this format efficient — a vector tile server fetches the small header range to read the index, then issues per-tile range requests for the bytes it needs.</p>
<p>The atomic-swap pattern uses S3's <code>CopyObject</code> operation: generation writes to <code>pmtiles/staging/{dataset_id}.pmtiles</code>, then the promotion Lambda issues a <code>CopyObject</code> from staging to <code>pmtiles/{dataset_id}.pmtiles</code>. S3 <code>CopyObject</code> is atomic from the consumer's perspective — the live URL either serves the old file or the new file, never a partial mix — and the new copy receives a new ETag. Vector tile servers that cache PMTiles directories keyed on ETag invalidate their cache automatically on the next access.</p>
<ac:structured-macro ac:name="info"><ac:rich-text-body><p><strong>In plain terms.</strong> the file is swapped in place without anyone seeing a half-written version, and the tile server notices the swap on its very next read without being restarted.</p></ac:rich-text-body></ac:structured-macro>
<p>For datasets that use the reviewed editing flow, additional PMTiles are produced per session under <code>drafts/</code>:</p>
<ac:structured-macro ac:name="code"><ac:plain-text-body><![CDATA[drafts/{dataset}/{session}/delta.pmtiles
drafts/{dataset}/{session}/diff.pmtiles]]></ac:plain-text-body></ac:structured-macro>
<ul><li><code>delta.pmtiles</code> contains only the edited features, tagged with an edit-operation marker (add/update/delete) and a validation-status marker.</li><li><code>diff.pmtiles</code> contains geometric differences (computed by spatial subtraction between session features and live features) tagged with a diff-type marker (geometry_added, geometry_removed, feature_added, feature_deleted, attributes_only).</li></ul>
<ac:structured-macro ac:name="info"><ac:rich-text-body><p><strong>In plain terms.</strong> reviewers see two small overlay layers — "what is changing" and "the shape of the change" — rather than having to diff two whole datasets in their head.</p></ac:rich-text-body></ac:structured-macro>
<p>These are served by the vector tile server at a path matching <code>/tiles/vector/drafts/...</code> so a reviewer can render them in a map client.</p>
<h2>Raster data: Cloud-Optimized GeoTIFFs</h2>
<p>Raster data is stored as <strong>COGs</strong> under <code>cogs/</code>. COGs are tiled internally with overviews; clients (GDAL-aware) can issue HTTP range requests for exactly the bytes needed for a given zoom level and area.</p>
<p>Mosaics across multiple COGs are described by <strong>MosaicJSON</strong> files under <code>mosaics/</code>. A MosaicJSON references many COG URLs and describes their spatial arrangement; tile servers query the mosaic to find which COGs cover a given tile and composite the result.</p>
<h2>History: row-level slowly-changing-dimension (SCD2)</h2>
<p>Per-row history is stored under <code>history/{dataset}/</code> as flat (non-partitioned) Parquet files. Each row carries SCD2 columns:</p>
<table><tbody><tr><th>Column</th><th>Meaning</th></tr><tr><td><code>_valid_from</code></td><td>Timestamp the row version became active.</td></tr><tr><td><code>_valid_to</code></td><td>Timestamp the row version was superseded (null for current).</td></tr><tr><td><code>_is_current</code></td><td>Boolean — true if <code>_valid_to</code> is null.</td></tr><tr><td><code>_change_type</code></td><td><code>insert</code>, <code>update</code>, or <code>delete</code>.</td></tr><tr><td><code>_job_id</code></td><td>The pipeline job that produced this version.</td></tr></tbody></table>
<p><strong>Write pattern</strong> (per promotion):</p>
<ul><li>New row versions and inserts are written to <code>{job_id}_delta.parquet</code>.</li><li>For updates and deletes, lightweight closeout files (<code>{job_id}_closeout.parquet</code> containing <code>id</code>, <code>_valid_to</code>, <code>_is_current=false</code>) record that the prior version is no longer current.</li></ul>
<p><strong>Initial snapshot</strong>: when history is first enabled on a large dataset, a single <code>_initial.parquet</code> is written with the current dataset state. The history vacuum (see below) compacts deltas but never rewrites the initial snapshot.</p>
<p><strong>Read pattern</strong>: queries glob over <code>history/{dataset}/**/*.parquet</code>. Predicate pushdown on <code>_valid_from</code>/<code>_valid_to</code> makes point-in-time queries efficient. A "feature X as of time T" query reads only the row versions whose validity window covers T.</p>
<p><strong>Vacuum</strong>: a scheduled task merges small delta and closeout files into monthly compacted files. The initial snapshot is left untouched. Retention is configurable per dataset (default one year).</p>
<p><strong>Opt-in</strong>: history is enabled per dataset via the dataset registry. Datasets without history enabled do not produce history rows.</p>
<p><strong>Best-effort</strong>: history writes are best-effort relative to promotion. A failed history write logs the error but does not fail the pipeline job; a missing history entry is acceptable but an incomplete promotion is not.</p>
<h2>Event log</h2>
<p><code>metadata/dataset_events/</code> holds per-dataset operational events as Parquet files. Events include:</p>
<ul><li>Pipeline state transitions</li><li>Schema changes</li><li>Validation rule changes</li><li>SQL edits</li><li>Administrative actions on the dataset</li></ul>
<p>A scheduled compactor merges small per-event files into monthly archives, mirroring the history vacuum pattern.</p>
<h1>DynamoDB layout</h1>
<p>A small number of DynamoDB tables hold operational state. The policies table uses a <strong>single-table design</strong> (multiple item types distinguished by partition-key prefix). Other tables are simpler: one item type per table where access patterns or TTL requirements diverge. All tables use <strong>on-demand</strong> billing and have <strong>point-in-time recovery (PITR)</strong> enabled.</p>
<h2>Policies table (single-table design)</h2>
<p>All authorisation policies live in one DynamoDB table. Partition-key prefixes (<code>CEILING#</code>, <code>GROUP#</code>, <code>MEMBER#</code>, etc.) distinguish item types; sort-key patterns enable the queries each domain needs in a single round trip:</p>
<table><tbody><tr><th>Partition key</th><th>Sort key</th><th>Item type</th></tr><tr><td><code>CEILING#{idp_group_id}</code></td><td><code>META</code></td><td>Ceiling mapping (role_ceiling, scope_ceiling)</td></tr><tr><td><code>GROUP#{group_id}</code></td><td><code>META</code></td><td>Platform group metadata (name, description, claims JSON)</td></tr><tr><td><code>GROUP#{group_id}</code></td><td><code>DATASET#{dataset_id}</code></td><td>Group↔dataset link</td></tr><tr><td><code>GROUP#{group_id}</code></td><td><code>PROJECT#{project_id}</code></td><td>Group↔project link</td></tr><tr><td><code>MEMBER#{user_id}</code></td><td><code>GROUP#{group_id}</code></td><td>Platform group membership (role, joined_at)</td></tr><tr><td><code>PROJECT#{project_id}</code></td><td><code>META</code></td><td>Project metadata</td></tr><tr><td><code>PROJECT#{project_id}</code></td><td><code>GROUP#{group_id}</code></td><td>Project↔group link</td></tr><tr><td><code>DATASET#{dataset_id}</code></td><td><code>RLS#{column_name}</code></td><td>Row-level security rule (claim, operator)</td></tr><tr><td><code>INVITE#{email}</code></td><td><code>GROUP#{group_id}</code></td><td>Pending invitation (role, invited_by, invited_at)</td></tr></tbody></table>
<p>This single-table design is deliberate: every authorisation query is a DynamoDB <code>Query</code> on a partition key, returning all the items the authoriser needs for that subject (ceiling, memberships, dataset grants, claims) in one round trip. Conditional writes on the <code>version</code> attribute provide optimistic locking where concurrent writes are possible.</p>
<h2>API keys table</h2>
<p>Separate from policies because access patterns differ (one item per credential, no relational lookups):</p>
<table><tbody><tr><th>Field</th><th>Description</th></tr><tr><td><code>APIKEY#{sha256(key)}</code> (partition key)</td><td>The key hash</td></tr><tr><td><code>owner_type</code></td><td><code>user</code> or <code>group</code></td></tr><tr><td><code>owner_id</code></td><td>The owning user or group identifier</td></tr><tr><td><code>active</code></td><td>Boolean — flip to false to revoke</td></tr><tr><td><code>description</code></td><td>Human-readable label</td></tr><tr><td><code>created_at</code></td><td>Issuance timestamp</td></tr><tr><td><code>scope</code></td><td><code>public</code> (default) — reserved for future use</td></tr></tbody></table>
<h2>Datasets table</h2>
<p>The dataset registry. Holds public-facing metadata, lineage, and operational status.</p>
<table><tbody><tr><th>Field</th><th>Description</th></tr><tr><td><code>DATASET#{dataset_id}</code> (partition key)</td><td>Dataset identifier</td></tr><tr><td><code>name</code></td><td>Human-readable name</td></tr><tr><td><code>data_type</code></td><td><code>vector</code>, <code>raster</code>, or <code>table</code></td></tr><tr><td><code>public</code></td><td>Boolean — included in anonymous access if true</td></tr><tr><td><code>active</code></td><td>Boolean — included in catalogue listings</td></tr><tr><td><code>metadata</code></td><td>Free-form JSON: description, attribution, lineage, contact</td></tr><tr><td><code>schema</code></td><td>JSON Schema describing the vector dataset's attribute columns</td></tr><tr><td><code>id_column</code></td><td>The unique-identifier column (required for cross-partition deduplication)</td></tr><tr><td><code>min_zoom</code>, <code>max_zoom</code></td><td>Tile generation parameters</td></tr><tr><td><code>partition_zoom</code></td><td>Spatial partitioning zoom for <code>source/</code> (typically 6)</td></tr><tr><td><code>review_required</code></td><td>Boolean — edits go through a review step before promotion</td></tr><tr><td><code>history_enabled</code></td><td>Boolean — write SCD2 history on each promotion</td></tr><tr><td><code>history_retention_days</code></td><td>Optional retention setting (default 365)</td></tr><tr><td><code>pipeline_status</code></td><td><code>idle</code>, <code>processing</code>, or <code>failed</code></td></tr><tr><td><code>needs_review</code></td><td>Boolean — set when dataset-sync detects a new dataset that an admin should classify</td></tr></tbody></table>
<h2>Jobs table</h2>
<p>Pipeline jobs. One item per pipeline execution.</p>
<table><tbody><tr><th>Field</th><th>Description</th></tr><tr><td><code>JOB#{job_id}</code> (partition key)</td><td>Job identifier</td></tr><tr><td><code>dataset_id</code></td><td>The dataset this job targets</td></tr><tr><td><code>status</code></td><td><code>pending</code>, <code>queued</code>, <code>validating</code>, <code>generating</code>, <code>complete</code>, <code>failed</code>, <code>cancelled</code></td></tr><tr><td><code>operation</code></td><td><code>add</code>, <code>update</code>, <code>patch</code>, <code>delete</code>, <code>replace</code>, <code>regenerate</code>, <code>sql_edit</code></td></tr><tr><td><code>created_at</code>, <code>updated_at</code>, <code>completed_at</code></td><td>Timestamps</td></tr><tr><td><code>payload_key</code></td><td>Object-storage key of the upload (under <code>landing/</code>)</td></tr><tr><td><code>execution_arn</code></td><td>Workflow execution identifier</td></tr><tr><td><code>error</code></td><td>Human-readable error message on failure</td></tr></tbody></table>
<p>A <strong>DynamoDB Global Secondary Index (GSI)</strong> on <code>(dataset_id, status)</code> supports the per-dataset concurrency check (one active job per dataset). The check is implemented as a <code>Query</code> on the GSI for <code>status IN (pending, validating, generating)</code>; the result determines whether a new job is created as <code>pending</code> or <code>queued</code>.</p>
<h2>Edit sessions table</h2>
<p>Sessions for reviewed editing. One item per session.</p>
<table><tbody><tr><th>Field</th><th>Description</th></tr><tr><td><code>SESSION#{session_id}</code> (partition key)</td><td>Session identifier</td></tr><tr><td><code>dataset_id</code></td><td>Target dataset</td></tr><tr><td><code>owner_id</code></td><td>User who created the session</td></tr><tr><td><code>status</code></td><td>See <ac:link><ri:page ri:content-title="11 — Editing Pipeline"/><ac:plain-text-link-body><![CDATA[11 Editing Pipeline]]></ac:plain-text-link-body></ac:link> for the state machine</td></tr><tr><td><code>version</code></td><td>Optimistic-locking counter</td></tr><tr><td><code>created_at</code>, <code>updated_at</code>, <code>submitted_at</code>, <code>reviewed_at</code></td><td>Timestamps</td></tr><tr><td><code>reviewer_id</code></td><td>Approver's user identifier (must differ from <code>owner_id</code>)</td></tr><tr><td><code>payload_summary</code></td><td>Counts of adds/updates/deletes</td></tr><tr><td><code>validation_summary</code></td><td>Aggregate validation results</td></tr></tbody></table>
<p>DynamoDB <strong>GSIs</strong> on <code>(dataset_id, status)</code>, <code>(owner_id, updated_at)</code>, and <code>(reviewer_id, status)</code> support the operator queries.</p>
<p><strong>Session expiry (DynamoDB TTL):</strong></p>
<ul><li>Sessions in terminal states (<code>promoted</code>, <code>rejected</code>, <code>cancelled</code>) carry a DynamoDB TTL six months in the future. The TTL field is set on transition to the terminal state.</li><li>Sessions in non-terminal states (<code>draft</code>, <code>uploading</code>, <code>submitted</code>, <code>validating</code>, <code>reviewing</code>, <code>failed</code>) carry a DynamoDB TTL refreshed to one month from the most recent activity. An abandoned session is removed automatically.</li></ul>
<p>The DynamoDB TTL governs the <em>session record</em> in the <code>edit-sessions</code> table. It is independent of the S3 lifecycle rule for the <code>drafts/</code> prefix (see "Storage class and lifecycle" below), which governs the <em>content files</em> (delta and diff PMTiles, validation results). The two run on different cadences and need not match.</p>
<h2>Validation checks and sequences</h2>
<p>User-defined validation rules:</p>
<table><tbody><tr><th>Partition key</th><th>Item type</th></tr><tr><td><code>CHECK#{check_id}</code></td><td>A single check: SQL template + parameter declarations + severity (<code>error</code>/<code>warning</code>)</td></tr><tr><td><code>VALSEQ#{sequence_id}</code></td><td>A named sequence of check identifiers, applied as a group</td></tr></tbody></table>
<p>Datasets reference an ordered list of validation sequences in their registry entry. The validation task applies them in order.</p>
<h1>Storage class and lifecycle</h1>
<p>The bucket carries an <strong>S3 Lifecycle policy</strong> that transitions objects to <strong>S3 Intelligent-Tiering</strong> after 30 days. All prefixes share that base rule except:</p>
<ul><li><code>pmtiles/</code> — live tile artefacts. Keep in Standard; never transition.</li><li><code>pmtiles/staging/</code> — short-lived; the promotion Lambda deletes the staging file on success. A safety-net lifecycle rule expires anything remaining after 1 day.</li><li><code>landing/</code> — short-lived; the promotion Lambda removes the upload on job completion. A safety-net lifecycle rule expires anything remaining after 7 days.</li><li><code>drafts/</code> — session content (delta and diff PMTiles, validation result JSON). Lifecycle rule deletes content after <strong>90 days</strong> regardless of session status — this is the <em>content-file</em> retention, distinct from the DynamoDB session-record TTL above. A still-active session whose drafts were lifecycle-deleted can re-run generation; the metadata persists in DynamoDB.</li></ul>
<p><strong>S3 Versioning</strong> is enabled on the bucket so that an accidental delete or overwrite can be recovered. The lifecycle policy includes a rule that expires non-current versions after 30 days to bound the cost.</p>
<h1>Access patterns at a glance</h1>
<table><tbody><tr><th>Operation</th><th>Path</th></tr><tr><td>Serve a vector tile</td><td>S3 byte-range read of <code>pmtiles/{dataset}.pmtiles</code></td></tr><tr><td>Serve a feature query</td><td>DuckDB read of <code>source/{dataset}/z=*/x=*/y=*/data.parquet</code> with partition predicate, then <code>DISTINCT ON (id)</code></td></tr><tr><td>Serve a raster tile</td><td>S3 byte-range read of one or more <code>cogs/</code> objects (possibly via a <code>mosaics/</code> MosaicJSON descriptor)</td></tr><tr><td>Ingest an edit</td><td>Client <code>PUT</code> to <code>landing/{dataset}/{job}/{file}</code> via S3 presigned URL</td></tr><tr><td>Promote an edit</td><td>S3 <code>CopyObject</code> <code>pmtiles/staging/{dataset}.pmtiles</code> → <code>pmtiles/{dataset}.pmtiles</code></td></tr><tr><td>Append history</td><td>Write <code>history/{dataset}/{job}_delta.parquet</code> (+ optional closeout)</td></tr><tr><td>Append event</td><td>Write <code>metadata/dataset_events/dataset_id={dataset}/{job}.parquet</code></td></tr><tr><td>Look up authorisation</td><td>DynamoDB <code>Query</code> on the policies-table partition</td></tr><tr><td>Look up a dataset</td><td>DynamoDB <code>GetItem</code> on the datasets table</td></tr><tr><td>Look up active jobs for a dataset</td><td>DynamoDB <code>Query</code> on the <code>(dataset_id, status)</code> GSI on the jobs table</td></tr></tbody></table>
<p>The whole design is built around these patterns being O(1) or O(touched partitions), never O(dataset size).</p>
