<p>This document describes day-to-day operations: monitoring, alarms, troubleshooting, scheduled maintenance, and disaster recovery considerations. It assumes the platform is deployed as described in <ac:link><ri:page ri:content-title="12 — Deployment"/><ac:plain-text-link-body><![CDATA[12 Deployment]]></ac:plain-text-link-body></ac:link>.</p>
<h1>Monitoring surface</h1>
<p>Two <strong>Amazon CloudWatch</strong> dashboards are recommended, with metrics drawn from CloudWatch metrics for ALB, API Gateway, CloudFront, ECS, Lambda, Step Functions, DynamoDB, and S3.</p>
<h2>Operations dashboard</h2>
<p>For platform operators. Tracks the health of the components themselves.</p>
<table><tbody><tr><th>Panel</th><th>Source</th><th>Purpose</th></tr><tr><td>ALB request rate, 4xx/5xx counts, p50/p95/p99 latency</td><td>CloudWatch (ALB metrics)</td><td>Detect traffic anomalies and latency drift</td></tr><tr><td>API Gateway HTTP API request rate, integration latency, authoriser duration</td><td>CloudWatch (API Gateway metrics)</td><td>Identify gateway-level issues</td></tr><tr><td>CloudFront cache hit rate, edge request counts, byte counts</td><td>CloudWatch (CloudFront metrics)</td><td>Quantify cache effectiveness</td></tr><tr><td>Fargate service task counts, CPU/memory utilisation, scaling actions</td><td>CloudWatch (ECS service metrics)</td><td>Capacity health</td></tr><tr><td>Lambda authoriser invocations, errors, cold-start init duration</td><td>CloudWatch (Lambda metrics)</td><td>Auth path health</td></tr><tr><td>Step Functions executions started/succeeded/failed, current running</td><td>CloudWatch (Step Functions metrics)</td><td>Editing pipeline health</td></tr><tr><td>S3 storage growth per prefix</td><td>S3 Storage Lens</td><td>Storage trend</td></tr><tr><td>DynamoDB throttling, latency, consumed capacity</td><td>CloudWatch (DynamoDB metrics)</td><td>Data layer health</td></tr></tbody></table>
<h2>Usage dashboard</h2>
<p>For platform owners and users.</p>
<table><tbody><tr><th>Panel</th><th>Purpose</th></tr><tr><td>Per-credential request counts (top 20)</td><td>Who is using the platform</td></tr><tr><td>Per-credential data egress</td><td>Volume per consumer</td></tr><tr><td>Per-service request breakdown</td><td>Which capabilities are exercised</td></tr><tr><td>Feature downloads (count, bytes)</td><td>OGC Features API usage</td></tr><tr><td>Tile requests (vector and raster)</td><td>Tile traffic</td></tr><tr><td>Editing activity (jobs per dataset, success/failure)</td><td>Edit workflow usage</td></tr><tr><td>Error rate by user</td><td>Identify clients with problems</td></tr></tbody></table>
<h1>Alarms</h1>
<p>A small set of alarms covers the failure modes that need human attention.</p>
<table><tbody><tr><th>Alarm</th><th>Condition</th><th>What it means</th></tr><tr><td>Load balancer 5xx rate</td><td>≥ 10 in 5 minutes for 2 periods</td><td>Backend errors, capacity, or configuration issue</td></tr><tr><td>Backend 5xx rate</td><td>≥ 20 in 5 minutes for 2 periods</td><td>Specific backend is failing</td></tr><tr><td>Load balancer p95 latency</td><td>&gt; 5 seconds for 3 periods</td><td>Slow responses; possible cold start storm or saturation</td></tr><tr><td>API gateway 5xx rate</td><td>≥ 10 in 5 minutes for 2 periods</td><td>Gateway or authoriser failures</td></tr><tr><td>Authoriser errors</td><td>≥ 5 in 5 minutes for 2 periods</td><td>Authoriser crashing</td></tr><tr><td>Container CPU (per service)</td><td>&gt; 80% for 3 periods</td><td>Service needs more capacity</td></tr><tr><td>Workflow engine failures</td><td>≥ 1 per period</td><td>Editing pipeline failure</td></tr><tr><td>Validation dead-letter queue depth</td><td>&gt; 0</td><td>Uploads failing to parse</td></tr></tbody></table>
<p>Each alarm should link to a runbook section below.</p>
<h1>Log sources</h1>
<table><tbody><tr><th>Source</th><th>Destination</th><th>Retention</th><th>Content</th></tr><tr><td>API Gateway HTTP API access logs</td><td>CloudWatch Logs</td><td>30 days</td><td><code>userId</code>, path, status, response length, latency</td></tr><tr><td>ALB access logs</td><td>S3 <code>alb-logs/</code> prefix</td><td>90 days</td><td>Client IP, path, status, latency</td></tr><tr><td>CloudFront standard logs</td><td>S3 <code>cloudfront-logs/</code> prefix</td><td>90 days</td><td>Edge location, bytes, URI, status, user agent</td></tr><tr><td>ECS / Fargate container logs</td><td>CloudWatch Logs</td><td>7 days</td><td>Application stdout/stderr</td></tr><tr><td>Lambda function logs</td><td>CloudWatch Logs</td><td>14 days</td><td>Per-invocation output and structured logs</td></tr><tr><td>VPC flow logs</td><td>CloudWatch Logs</td><td>7 days</td><td>Network traffic metadata</td></tr><tr><td>Dataset event log</td><td>S3 <code>metadata/dataset_events/</code></td><td>Indefinite (compacted monthly)</td><td>Per-dataset events (jobs, schema changes, SQL edits)</td></tr></tbody></table>
<h1>Common queries</h1>
<p>Useful queries to keep handy, expressed in <strong>CloudWatch Logs Insights</strong> syntax against the API Gateway access-log group:</p>
<p><strong>Top users by request count (last 24 hours)</strong>:</p>
<ac:structured-macro ac:name="code"><ac:plain-text-body><![CDATA[filter userId != '' and userId != 'anonymous'
| stats count(*) as requests by userId
| sort requests desc | limit 20]]></ac:plain-text-body></ac:structured-macro>
<p><strong>Data egress per user</strong>:</p>
<ac:structured-macro ac:name="code"><ac:plain-text-body><![CDATA[filter userId != '' and userId != 'anonymous'
| stats sum(responseLength) as bytes by userId
| sort bytes desc]]></ac:plain-text-body></ac:structured-macro>
<p><strong>Feature downloads by dataset</strong>:</p>
<ac:structured-macro ac:name="code"><ac:plain-text-body><![CDATA[filter path like '/features/v1/collections/'
| stats count(*) as requests by path
| sort requests desc]]></ac:plain-text-body></ac:structured-macro>
<p><strong>Job failures by dataset</strong>:</p>
<ac:structured-macro ac:name="code"><ac:plain-text-body><![CDATA[filter status = 'failed'
| stats count(*) as failures by dataset_id
| sort failures desc]]></ac:plain-text-body></ac:structured-macro>
<h1>Runbook — common failures</h1>
<h2>Service won't start</h2>
<p>Check container service logs and event history. The most common causes:</p>
<ol><li>Image not present — verify the image tag is in the image registry.</li><li>Task role permissions — verify the task IAM role can reach the key-value store and object storage.</li><li>Resource starvation — check whether the container cluster has capacity.</li><li>Health check failing — confirm the service is binding to the expected port and responding to the health endpoint.</li></ol>
<h2>Pipeline job stuck in <code>pending</code></h2>
<p>The job has been created but the workflow has not started:</p>
<ol><li>Check the dataset's <code>pipeline_status</code> — if another job is running, the new job is <code>queued</code>, not <code>pending</code>.</li><li>Check the workflow engine's execution history for the dataset — if no execution exists, the editing API's call to start the workflow may have failed silently.</li><li>Inspect the editing API logs for the corresponding job ID.</li><li>If genuinely stuck, manually invoke the workflow with the job's payload; mark the original job <code>failed</code> if duplicate is unsafe.</li></ol>
<h2>Pipeline job stuck in <code>validating</code> or <code>generating</code></h2>
<p>The container task has been launched but has not completed:</p>
<ol><li>List running container tasks for the validation or generation task definition.</li><li>Tail the task's logs to see where it is.</li><li>If the task has been running longer than the timeout, mark it failed via the failure handler.</li><li>If the task is making progress (logs continue), let it complete; check whether the workflow engine's per-task timeout is appropriately set.</li></ol>
<h2>Dead-letter queue has messages</h2>
<p>Messages in the validation DLQ indicate uploads that failed to be parsed and never started a workflow execution:</p>
<ol><li>Inspect the message bodies — they contain the original storage event.</li><li>Identify the offending object in <code>landing/</code>.</li><li>Determine the cause (corrupt file, unexpected format, missing job record).</li><li>If the upload was legitimate, manually trigger the workflow with the correct payload.</li><li>Delete the DLQ messages once handled.</li></ol>
<h2>Authoriser returning 401 unexpectedly</h2>
<p>Check, in order:</p>
<ol><li>Was the token issued by a trusted issuer? The trusted-issuers list is a deployment parameter.</li><li>Has the token expired?</li><li>Has the user's policy been recently changed? Cache TTL is up to 5 minutes; wait or invalidate.</li><li>Is the user's IdP group recognised by the ceiling table? An unknown group results in a denied request.</li><li>For API keys: is the key still <code>active</code> in the keys table?</li></ol>
<h2>CDN returning stale tiles after a promotion</h2>
<p>Either:</p>
<ul><li>The CDN invalidation in the promotion function did not complete; check the function logs.</li><li>The tile server cache has not picked up the new ETag; restart the affected task or wait for the cache TTL.</li></ul>
<h2>Cognito (or other IdP) user cannot sign in</h2>
<p>For Cognito specifically:</p>
<ol><li>Verify the user exists in the user pool.</li><li>Verify the user is <code>CONFIRMED</code> (not still <code>FORCE_CHANGE_PASSWORD</code> if invited).</li><li>Check the app client's allowed auth flows.</li></ol>
<p>For other IdPs, the relevant checks are IdP-specific and outside the platform's control.</p>
<h2>Key-value store throttling</h2>
<p>Either:</p>
<ul><li>A pathological access pattern (a hot partition); inspect the most-accessed partitions and consider splitting the workload.</li><li>A sudden traffic spike beyond on-demand capacity; check the cloud's provisioned/on-demand setting.</li><li>Cascading retries from a transient cloud-side issue; back off and retry.</li></ul>
<h1>Scheduled maintenance</h1>
<table><tbody><tr><th>Job</th><th>Cadence</th><th>Purpose</th></tr><tr><td>Dataset sync</td><td>Every 15 minutes</td><td>Reconcile registry with object storage</td></tr><tr><td>History vacuum</td><td>Daily</td><td>Compact per-job history into monthly archives</td></tr><tr><td>Event log compactor</td><td>Daily</td><td>Compact per-job events into monthly archives</td></tr><tr><td>Authoriser cache flush</td><td>None scheduled (TTL-driven)</td><td>Permissions propagate within minutes</td></tr></tbody></table>
<h1>Storage cost management</h1>
<p>The single S3 bucket carries an <strong>S3 Lifecycle policy</strong> that transitions objects to <strong>S3 Intelligent-Tiering</strong> after 30 days. Recommended additional rules (also documented in <ac:link><ri:page ri:content-title="04 — Data Layout"/><ac:plain-text-link-body><![CDATA[04 Data Layout]]></ac:plain-text-link-body></ac:link>):</p>
<ul><li><code>landing/</code> — delete after job completion (handled by promotion Lambda; lifecycle rule as backstop after 7 days).</li><li><code>pmtiles/staging/</code> — delete after promotion (handled by promotion Lambda; lifecycle rule after 1 day).</li><li><code>drafts/</code> — delete after <strong>90 days</strong> regardless of session status. This governs the <em>content files</em> (delta and diff PMTiles, validation results) in S3. It is distinct from the <strong>DynamoDB TTL</strong> on the <code>edit-sessions</code> table, which expires the <em>session record</em> after one month of inactivity (non-terminal) or six months (terminal). The two mechanisms can run on different schedules without coordination — a session whose drafts content has been lifecycle-deleted can still be inspected via its DynamoDB record and re-generated if needed.</li><li>Old <code>history/</code> archives — transition to <strong>S3 Glacier Deep Archive</strong> after one year for datasets with long retention requirements.</li></ul>
<h1>Disaster recovery</h1>
<h2>Recovery point objectives</h2>
<table><tbody><tr><th>Resource</th><th>RPO</th></tr><tr><td>S3 (Versioning enabled)</td><td>0 — object versioning preserves prior states</td></tr><tr><td>DynamoDB (PITR enabled)</td><td>5 minutes (DynamoDB Point-In-Time Recovery resolution)</td></tr><tr><td>Cognito User Pool / external IdP</td><td>Provider-dependent</td></tr></tbody></table>
<h2>Recovery time objectives</h2>
<table><tbody><tr><th>Scenario</th><th>RTO</th></tr><tr><td>Loss of a single service</td><td>Minutes — redeploy from IaC</td></tr><tr><td>Loss of the entire deployment</td><td>Hours — re-bootstrap from IaC; data is intact in object storage and the key-value store</td></tr><tr><td>Loss of an entire cloud region</td><td>Hours plus data restore — requires cross-region replication of object storage and key-value store</td></tr></tbody></table>
<h2>Tested DR</h2>
<p>DR drills should exercise:</p>
<ol><li>Re-deploying the IaC into a clean account against an existing data store. The expectation is that the platform is fully operational after the deployment completes.</li><li>Restoring the key-value store to a point in time and verifying authorisation policies and dataset registries are intact.</li><li>For high-availability deployments: failing over to a secondary region (if cross-region replication is configured).</li></ol>
<p>The platform's design — stateless services, data in durable storage — makes the deployment-side of DR a normal redeploy. The data side relies on the durability and recoverability of the chosen object storage and key-value store, both of which offer multi-AZ durability by default.</p>
<h1>Capacity planning</h1>
<p>Two dimensions to plan:</p>
<p><strong>Read traffic</strong> is dominated by tile requests. CDN cache hit rate is the leading indicator: at high hit rates, backend load is decoupled from request volume. Capacity for the vector and raster tile servers should be planned for the unique tile rate (cache-miss rate × request rate), not the total request rate.</p>
<p><strong>Edit traffic</strong> is dominated by workflow executions. Validation and generation tasks scale per execution; the limiting factor is concurrent workflow executions and container cluster capacity. Plan for peak concurrent edit submissions across all datasets.</p>
<p>The authoriser and the function-runtime services scale per request; their cost is proportional to request count, with negligible per-instance overhead.</p>
<h1>Cost shape</h1>
<p>In <code>off</code> mode, baseline cost approaches the storage and registry minimums. Storage cost is proportional to data volume; key-value store on-demand costs are proportional to request count; the CDN charges for transfer.</p>
<p>In <code>minimal</code> mode, baseline cost adds the always-running container service tasks (one per service group's services). For a deployment with vector tiles, query layer, and editing enabled, this is a small number of tasks at modest sizing.</p>
<p>In <code>performance</code> mode, baseline cost adds the pre-warmed task count at the larger CPU/memory allocations. This is the highest steady-state cost.</p>
<p>A meaningful cost optimisation, especially in <code>off</code> and <code>minimal</code> modes, is removing NAT gateways (where used) and replacing them with private endpoints to the cloud's managed services (key-value store, object storage, container registry). The platform requires no outbound internet egress for its read or write paths; running private-only is feasible.</p>
<h1>Bootstrap</h1>
<p>A fresh deployment requires a one-time bootstrap to create the first administrator:</p>
<ol><li>Deploy the authoriser stack and the editing-pipeline stack.</li><li>Run a bootstrap script that:</li><li>Creates the first user in the IdP.</li><li>Maps that user's IdP group to a ceiling with the <code>platform_admin</code> role.</li><li>Creates a platform-admins group and adds the user to it.</li><li>The user can now sign in and manage everything else through the admin REST API.</li></ol>
<p>After bootstrap, no further direct writes to the key-value store should be needed; the admin API covers all operations.</p>
