<p>This document describes how external systems and users connect to the platform. It is the consumer's-eye view: what each client type sends, what it receives, what authentication flow to use.</p>
<h1>Client types</h1>
<p>The platform serves four principal client classes:</p>
<table><tbody><tr><th>Client class</th><th>Examples</th><th>Auth</th></tr><tr><td>Desktop GIS</td><td>QGIS, ArcGIS Pro, ArcGIS Enterprise Portal</td><td>API key (header or query parameter)</td></tr><tr><td>Web maps</td><td>Browser-based map viewers, web applications</td><td>OIDC JWT (interactive sign-in) or API key</td></tr><tr><td>Programmatic clients</td><td>Scripts, data-pipeline integrations</td><td>API key</td></tr><tr><td>Server-to-server</td><td>Other platforms consuming this one's data</td><td>API key (group-scoped)</td></tr></tbody></table>
<h1>Authentication options</h1>
<h2>OIDC sign-in (interactive)</h2>
<p>For users of a web application. The web app:</p>
<ol><li>Redirects the user to the identity provider's sign-in flow.</li><li>Receives an OIDC ID token from the provider on callback.</li><li>Sends the token as <code>Authorization: Bearer &lt;token&gt;</code> on subsequent platform requests.</li><li>Refreshes the token before expiry using the provider's refresh-token flow.</li></ol>
<p>The platform validates the token against the configured trusted issuers and resolves the user's permissions per <ac:link><ri:page ri:content-title="03 — Authorisation"/><ac:plain-text-link-body><![CDATA[03 Authorisation]]></ac:plain-text-link-body></ac:link>.</p>
<h2>API key (everything else)</h2>
<p>A user with a valid token, or an administrator, creates an API key:</p>
<ac:structured-macro ac:name="code"><ac:plain-text-body><![CDATA[POST /rest/auth/me/apikey            (self-service, for the calling user)
POST /rest/auth/apikeys              (admin, with explicit owner)]]></ac:plain-text-body></ac:structured-macro>
<p>The response contains the raw key, returned exactly once. Subsequent requests send the key as:</p>
<ac:structured-macro ac:name="code"><ac:plain-text-body><![CDATA[X-Api-Key: <raw_key>]]></ac:plain-text-body></ac:structured-macro>
<p>A user-scoped API key inherits the calling user's permissions. A group-scoped API key inherits the group's datasets as <code>viewer</code>. Group-scoped keys are the canonical choice for desktop GIS teams.</p>
<p>API keys are revoked by setting the <code>active</code> flag to false in the DynamoDB <code>api-keys</code> table; revocation takes effect within one minute (the authoriser Lambda's warm-container LRU cache TTL).</p>
<h1>QGIS</h1>
<h2>WMTS connection</h2>
<p>For raster layers and (via redirect) vector layers exposed as raster.</p>
<ol><li>Layer → Add Layer → Add WM(T)S Layer.</li><li>New connection:</li><li>Name: meaningful label.</li><li>URL: <code>https://&lt;cdn&gt;/wmts?service=WMTS&amp;request=GetCapabilities</code></li><li>Authentication tab → custom HTTP header:</li><li>Header name: <code>X-Api-Key</code></li><li>Header value: the raw API key.</li><li>Connect → select layer → Add.</li></ol>
<p>QGIS sends the <code>X-Api-Key</code> header on every tile request. The CDN caches per-key.</p>
<h2>WMS connection</h2>
<p>Same as WMTS but the URL is <code>https://&lt;cdn&gt;/wms?service=WMS&amp;request=GetCapabilities</code>.</p>
<h2>OGC API Features connection</h2>
<p>For vector features as features (not as tiles), with access to attributes.</p>
<ol><li>Layer → Add Layer → Add WFS / OGC API Features Layer.</li><li>New connection:</li><li>URL: <code>https://&lt;cdn&gt;/features/v1</code></li><li>Add the <code>X-Api-Key</code> header as for WMTS.</li><li>Connect → select collection → Add.</li></ol>
<p>The OGC Features API filters collections by the API key's group datasets and applies row-level security.</p>
<h1>ArcGIS</h1>
<h2>ArcGIS Enterprise Portal — vector tile service</h2>
<p>The platform exposes vector tile layers via an Esri-compatible adapter.</p>
<ol><li>Content → New Item → URL.</li><li>URL: <code>https://&lt;cdn&gt;/esri/vectortiles/{source}/VectorTileServer</code></li><li>The platform supplies VectorTileServer metadata, a Mapbox GL v8 style, and tiles in <code>.pbf</code> form.</li></ol>
<p>To pass an API key with ArcGIS requests, configure the portal item's request headers or proxy the requests through a service that adds the header.</p>
<h2>ArcGIS Pro — WMTS</h2>
<p>ArcGIS Pro consumes WMTS via Add Data → Add Layer From URL with the WMTS GetCapabilities URL. Authentication is configured per the Pro version's documentation.</p>
<h1>First-party web map client</h1>
<p>The platform ships a bundled web application — see <ac:link><ri:page ri:content-title="15 — Map Client (Web Application)"/><ac:plain-text-link-body><![CDATA[15 Map Client]]></ac:plain-text-link-body></ac:link> — built on React and MapLibre, with embedded GraphiQL, schema-driven editing, reviewed-editing approvals, live job tracking, and dataset history browsing. It consumes every public surface and is the recommended starting point for users who want a working spatial workspace without writing one. The rest of this document covers other client types — desktop GIS variants, generic web maps, and programmatic clients — that integrate against the same APIs.</p>
<h1>Generic web map clients</h1>
<p>For map libraries (MapLibre, Leaflet, OpenLayers) used outside the first-party client:</p>
<table><tbody><tr><th>Source type</th><th>URL pattern</th><th>Auth</th></tr><tr><td>Vector tile (TileJSON)</td><td><code>https://&lt;cdn&gt;/tiles/vector/{dataset}/tile.json</code></td><td>Header via XHR or token in URL where supported</td></tr><tr><td>Vector tile (direct)</td><td><code>https://&lt;cdn&gt;/tiles/vector/{dataset}/{z}/{x}/{y}.mvt</code></td><td>Same</td></tr><tr><td>Raster tile XYZ</td><td><code>https://&lt;cdn&gt;/tiles/raster/.../{z}/{x}/{y}.png</code></td><td>Same</td></tr><tr><td>WMTS</td><td><code>https://&lt;cdn&gt;/wmts?service=WMTS&amp;...</code></td><td>Header</td></tr><tr><td>Features GeoJSON</td><td><code>https://&lt;cdn&gt;/features/v1/collections/{id}/items?bbox=...</code></td><td>Header</td></tr></tbody></table>
<p>Most map libraries support setting custom request headers via a transform or fetch override. For public datasets, no auth is needed.</p>
<h1>Programmatic clients</h1>
<p>For scripts and integrations, two patterns:</p>
<h2>Direct REST/HTTP</h2>
<p>Use any HTTP client; send <code>X-Api-Key</code> on every request. The platform's REST surfaces follow standard JSON conventions.</p>
<h2>CLI wrapper</h2>
<p>A small CLI wrapper can manage API key acquisition and refresh. A reference implementation typically:</p>
<ul><li>Stores the user's credentials in a local configuration directory.</li><li>Acquires JWTs from the IdP on demand.</li><li>Caches the JWT for its lifetime; refreshes on expiry.</li><li>Adds <code>Authorization</code> or <code>X-Api-Key</code> to outbound requests transparently.</li></ul>
<p>Such a wrapper makes manual operations (<code>GET /rest/auth/me</code>, <code>POST /rest/auth/groups</code>, etc.) low-friction without the user managing tokens directly.</p>
<h1>Onboarding a new consumer</h1>
<p>The standard onboarding flow for a new partner team or service:</p>
<ac:structured-macro ac:name="mermaid-cloud"><ac:plain-text-body><![CDATA[sequenceDiagram
    autonumber
    participant Admin
    participant Platform
    participant Consumer

    Admin->>Platform: Create platform group<br/>(optional default claims)
    Admin->>Platform: Link datasets to group
    alt RLS needed
        Admin->>Platform: Configure RLS rule(s) on dataset(s)
    end
    Admin->>Platform: Create group-scoped API key
    Platform-->>Admin: Raw API key (once)
    Admin->>Consumer: Securely deliver key
    Consumer->>Platform: Requests with X-Api-Key
    Platform-->>Consumer: Filtered data per group + RLS]]></ac:plain-text-body></ac:structured-macro>
<p>For interactive users rather than service consumers, replace step 3 with an invitation:</p>
<ac:structured-macro ac:name="code"><ac:plain-text-body><![CDATA[POST /rest/auth/invites { "email": "...", "group_id": "...", "role": "..." }]]></ac:plain-text-body></ac:structured-macro>
<p>The user is invited via email; on first sign-in, the post-authentication hook converts the invitation into a membership.</p>
<h1>Common request patterns</h1>
<h2>List collections the caller may access</h2>
<ac:structured-macro ac:name="code"><ac:plain-text-body><![CDATA[GET /features/v1/collections
Authorization: Bearer <token>    or    X-Api-Key: <key>]]></ac:plain-text-body></ac:structured-macro>
<h2>Query features in a bbox</h2>
<ac:structured-macro ac:name="code"><ac:plain-text-body><![CDATA[GET /features/v1/collections/parcels/items?bbox=144.9,-37.9,145.1,-37.8&limit=100]]></ac:plain-text-body></ac:structured-macro>
<h2>Fetch a single feature</h2>
<ac:structured-macro ac:name="code"><ac:plain-text-body><![CDATA[GET /features/v1/collections/parcels/items/12345]]></ac:plain-text-body></ac:structured-macro>
<h2>Fetch a vector tile</h2>
<ac:structured-macro ac:name="code"><ac:plain-text-body><![CDATA[GET /tiles/vector/parcels/12/3300/2100.mvt]]></ac:plain-text-body></ac:structured-macro>
<h2>Fetch a TileJSON descriptor</h2>
<ac:structured-macro ac:name="code"><ac:plain-text-body><![CDATA[GET /tiles/vector/parcels/tile.json]]></ac:plain-text-body></ac:structured-macro>
<h2>Submit a feature update through the editing API</h2>
<p>The editing flow is typically: create session, request a presigned upload URL, upload the file, finalise. Poll the job for status. See <ac:link><ri:page ri:content-title="11 — Editing Pipeline"/><ac:plain-text-link-body><![CDATA[11 Editing Pipeline]]></ac:plain-text-link-body></ac:link>.</p>
<ac:structured-macro ac:name="code"><ac:plain-text-body><![CDATA[POST   /edit-sessions                     { "dataset_id": "parcels" }
POST   /edit-sessions/{id}/uploads        (returns presigned URL)
PUT    <presigned URL>                    (upload the file)
POST   /edit-sessions/{id}/finalize       (kicks off the pipeline)
GET    /jobs/{id}                         (poll for status)]]></ac:plain-text-body></ac:structured-macro>
<h2>Issue a self-service API key</h2>
<ac:structured-macro ac:name="code"><ac:plain-text-body><![CDATA[POST /rest/auth/me/apikey { "description": "QGIS at desk", "scope": "viewer" }]]></ac:plain-text-body></ac:structured-macro>
<h1>Public access</h1>
<p>For public datasets (<code>public: true</code> in the registry), requests do not need credentials. The CDN serves public content from a single edge cache entry not keyed on credentials:</p>
<ac:structured-macro ac:name="code"><ac:plain-text-body><![CDATA[GET /tiles/vector/public-dataset/{z}/{x}/{y}.mvt
GET /features/v1/collections/public-dataset/items?bbox=...]]></ac:plain-text-body></ac:structured-macro>
<p>Anonymous requests succeed; the caller receives only public datasets in catalogue responses.</p>
<h1>Versioning and stability</h1>
<p>The platform's external surfaces follow these stability principles:</p>
<ul><li><strong>OGC API paths</strong> (<code>/features/v1/...</code>, <code>/coverages/v1/...</code>) carry a version in the path. Breaking changes increment the version.</li><li><strong>STAC paths</strong> follow STAC's own versioning (the STAC API spec carries the version).</li><li><strong>Tile paths</strong> (<code>/tiles/vector/...</code>, <code>/tiles/raster/...</code>, <code>/wmts/...</code>) are stable.</li><li><strong>Admin paths</strong> (<code>/rest/...</code>) are versioned implicitly; breaking changes are infrequent and announced.</li></ul>
<p>The query layer's GraphQL schema is introspectable and the schema's evolution follows GraphQL's deprecation conventions.</p>
<h1>What clients should expect</h1>
<ul><li><strong>Cold-start latency.</strong> In scale-to-zero deployments, the first request after idle may take tens of seconds to a couple of minutes (container services). Subsequent requests are fast.</li><li><strong>Cache effects.</strong> Tiles cache for seven days per credential at the edge; metadata caches for one hour. Permission changes are visible within five minutes.</li><li><strong>No reorderable response.</strong> OGC Features returns results in a consistent order (typically by feature ID).</li><li><strong>Standards conformance.</strong> OGC APIs, STAC, WMTS, WMS, TileJSON, MVT all conform to their respective specifications. Clients that work with other implementations of these standards should work here.</li></ul>
